Guide to the Decision Magazine Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Decision Magazine papers
1940-1942
MS 176
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.3
(2 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, drafts of articles and poems, legal documents, press releases, clippings and other papers of the magazine which was published in New York from January 1941 to February 1942 under the editorship of Klaus Mann. Correspondents and writers include W.H. Auden, André Gide, Sir Julian Huxley, Christopher Isherwood, Heinrich Mann, Thomas Mann, William Carlos Williams and Stefan Zweig. Also in the papers is the proof for an unpublished article by Vladimir Nabokov, "Soviet Literature 1940."
Decision
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Klaus Mann in 1942.
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence to Klaus Mann available on microfilm (164 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM30.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains both business and literary documentation of the history of the magazine. On the business side are legal and financial papers, photographs of art work printed in the magazine, clippings, press releases and advertising circulars. The literary history is recorded in the correspondence and in an incomplete set of drafts of articles and poems. Among those whose drafts (holograph or typescript) have survived are W.H. Auden, Stefan Zweig, Heinrich Mann and Muriel Rukeyser. Particularly interesting are the drafts by William Carlos Williams for an article on Pound and by Sir Julian Huxley for "The redefinition of freedom." Klaus Mann's editorials are almost all concerned with the dangers of Nazism to America and to western culture. Also in the papers is the proof for an unpublished article by Vladimir Nabokov, "Soviet Literature 1940."
Biographical / Historical
Decision: A review of free culture was founded in New York in December 1940 by Klaus Mann (1906-1949), a refugee writer and son of Thomas Mann. Conceived as an anti-fascist organ as well as a literary review, the magazine, from its very first issue in January 1941, was for the most part an American forum for exiled European artists and intellectuals. In addition to Thomas Mann, who contributed articles without a fee, the magazine published Stefan Zweig, Heinrich Mann, Julien Green, Vladimir Nabokov, Marc Chagall, Fernand Léger and anti-Nazi English writers such as W.H. Auden, Christopher Isherwood and Stephen Spender.
Yet a number of American writers, artists and educators also took an interest in Decision. In the issue of September 1941, William Carlos Williams contributed a strong attack on Ezra Pound, who was then making broadcasts for Mussolini. Max Lerner wrote several articles, and for a brief period Muriel Rukeyser was an associate editor. The correspondence contains letters from many others expressing support for the magazine. On the permanent editorial board of directors were Stephen Vincent Benét, Louis Adamic, Horace Gregory, Robert Nathan, Ernest Boyd, Vincent Sheehan and Robert E. Sherwood. At the end of 1941, Decision found itself in grave financial difficulties and was forced to cease publication with the issue of January/February 1942.
Decision; Journalism; Periodicals; Radicalism; Political refugees; World War, 1939-1945; United States -- Intellectual life; Adamic, Louis, 1899-1951; Ascoli, Max, 1898-1978; Benét, Stephen Vincent, 1898-1943; Breuer, Bessie, 1893-1975; Chagall, Marc, 1887-1985; Childs, Stephen Lawford, 1896-1943; Clough, T. Gardner; Connolly, Cyril, 1903-1974; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979; Field, Marshall, 1893-1956; Fisher, Peter Thomas; Fletcher, Angus, 1883-; Frank, Bruno, 1887-1945; Gide, André, 1869-1951; Green, Julien, 1900-1998; Hartman, A. (Alan); Heller, Gesine; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963; Isherwood, Christopher, 1904-1986; Kaplan, Percy; Kaufmann, Edgar, 1910-1989; La Touche, John Treville, 1917-; Landau, M. A. (Mikhail Aleksandrovich); Lerner, Max, 1902-1992; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Mann, Heinrich, 1871-1950; Mann, Klaus, 1906-1949; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; McCullers, Carson, 1917-1967; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977; O'Brien, Justin, 1906-1968; Paley, William S. (William Samuel), 1901-1990; Prokosch, Frederic, 1908-1989; Quinn, Kerker; Rosenbloom, Charles J., 1898-1973; Sherwood, Robert E. (Robert Emmet), 1896-1955; Singsen, F. M.; Spender, Stephen, 1909-1995; Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961; Tully, Jim, 1886-1947; Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944; Von Stroheim, Erich, 1885-1957; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946; Young, Stanley, 1906-1975; Zweig, Stefan, 1881-1942
- Inventory, 1940-1942; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Huxley, Aldous, 1940 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Isherwood, Christopher, 1940 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1940 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mann, Heinrich, 1940 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paley, William S., 1940 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sherwood, Robert E., 1940 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Tully, Jim, 1940 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1940 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Wells, H.G., 1940 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adamic, Louis, 1941 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aldanov, M., 1941 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Childs, S. Lawford, 1941 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Connelly, Cyril, 1941 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Connelly, Cyril, Matson, Peter and Spender, Stephen, 1941 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fisher, Peter Thomas, 1941 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fletcher, Angus, 1941 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gide, André, 1941 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mann, Klaus, 1941 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Thompson, Dorothy, 1941 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ascoli, Max, 1941 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1941 June 24, July 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Farrell, James T., 1941 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Field, Marshall, 1941 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Frank, Bruno, 1941 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Free World, 1941 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Green, Julien, 1941 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - McCullers, Carson, 1941 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1941 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Spender, Stephen, 1941 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Zweig, Stefan, 1941 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified, 1941 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Adamic, Louis, 1941 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Breuer, Bessie, 1941 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Clough, T. Gardner, 1941 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Green, Julien, 1941 October 12, October 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lerner, Max, 1941 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1941 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - O'Brien, Justin, 1941 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Prokosch, Frederic, 1941 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Singsen, F.M., 1941 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rosenbloom, Charles J., 1941 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Zweig, Stefan, 1941 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Heller, Gesine, 1941 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mann, Klaus, 1941 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pound, Ezra, 1941 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Prokosch, Frederic, 1941 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Quinn, Ker Ker, 1941 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Young, Stanley, 1941 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Zweig, Stefan, 1941 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Benét, Stephen Vincent, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Breuer, Bessie, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chagall, Marc, 1942 February (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Isherwood, Christopher, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Kaplan, Percy, 1942 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Kaufmann, Edgar, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - La Touche, John Treville, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lerner, Max, 1942 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - McCullers, Carson, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rukeyser, Muriel and Mann, Klaus, 1942 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stroheim, Erich von, 1942 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Tully, Jim, 1942 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Drafts and lists of contributors' fees
    - 1941 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Isherwood, Christopher (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Mann, Heinrich (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Zweig, Stefan (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1941 February (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Mann, Golo (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1941 March (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Bishop, John Peale (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Muni, Paul (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1941 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1941 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1941 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1941 July-August (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1941 September (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Huxley, Julian (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Pound, Ezra (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Williams, William Carlos (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1941 October (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Mann, Heinrich (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1941 November-December (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Mann, Klaus (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Spender, Stephen (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - undated
      - Isherwood, Christopher (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Mann, Thomas (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Business papers
    - Proofs, 1941 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Circulars and press releases, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Adamic, Louis (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Benés, Edward (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Benét, Stephen Vincent (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Frank, Bruno (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Gregory, Horace (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Kingdon, Frank (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Kirchwey, Freda (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Maugham, W. Somerset (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Nathan, Robert (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Sheehan, Vincent (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Sherwood, Robert E. (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - van Paassen, Pierre (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Zweig, Stefan (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Photographs of pictures reproduced in Decision (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Legal documents, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Galleys and formats, 1941 (Box 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes galleys and proofs for the magazine, including the proof for an unpublished article by Vladimir Nabokov, "Soviet Literature 1940."